[MUSIC]
In our last lesson we talked
about the activity class.
And I showed you how one activity can
programmatically start another activity by
first creating an intent object and
then by passing that
intent to a method such as start
activity or start activity for result.
Today, we are going to take
a deeper look at intents.
We'll discuss how they are created and
processed as they're used in
starting other activities.
And I'll begin by presenting
the intent class itself.
I'll talk about how they're created,
what fields they have, and
what information those fields contain.
After that, I'll talk about the two
ways in which Android decides which
activities should be started when a method
such as start activity is called.
First, I'll talk about
explicit activation in which
intents specifically name
the activity they want to start.
And second, I'll start about implicit
activation, where intents don't select
a target activity but instead describe
the operation they want to be performed.
After which Android finds and
then starts the activity that
can perform that operation.
The intent class is basically
a data structure that serves at
least two purposes in Android.
One, it can specify an operation
that you want to perform.
And two, it can represent an event that
has occurred in the system that you
want to notify other components about.
Today however we're going to
focus on just the first of these.
Using intents to specify operations
that you want performed.
And we'll leave the second of these,
using intents for
event notification, for a later lesson
when we talk about broadcast receivers.
Now you can think of intents as
providing a kind of language for
specifying operations that
you want to have performed.
In essence, intents give you
an easy way to say things like,
I want to select a contact.
I want to take a photo.
I want to dial a phone number.
Or I want to display a map.
So in practice,
intents are usually constructed by one
activity that wants some work to be done.
And then Android uses that intent
to start another activity that can
perform the desired work.
So let's talk now about the kinds
of information that can be
specified within an intent.
For example, we'll talk about
intent fields including action,
data, category, MIME type,
target component, extras, and flags.
An intent's action field is
a string that represents or
names the operation to be performed.
Some built in examples include,
action_dial, which means I want
someone to dial a phone number.
Action_edit, I want someone to display
some data for the user to edit.
Action_sync, I would like
to synchronize some data on
my device with data on a server.
An action_main,
I want to start an activity as
the initial activity of an application.
You can set an intent's
action in several ways.
For example, you can pass an action string
as a parameter to the intent constructor.
Alternatively you can create an empty
intent and then call the set action method
on it, passing the action
string again as a parameter.
Intents also has a data field
which represents data that is
associated with the intent.
Now that data is formatted as
a uniform resource identifier, or URI.
And one example of intent data is a
geo-schemed URI which indicates map data.
You might also remember that we
saw something exactly like this in
earlier lessons as part of those
map location applications.
Another example is a tell schemed URI,
indicating a phone number
that you want dialed.
And note that the strings that represent
the underlying data are first being passed
through the Uri.parse method, which takes
that string and then returns a URI object.
You can set the intents
data in a variety of ways.
For instance, you can pass it
directly to the intents constructor.
Or you can create an empty intent and then
use the setData method to set the data for
that intent.
The intent category represents
additional information about
the kinds of components that can handle or
should handle this intent.
Some examples include category_browsable.
Which means that the activity can be
invoked by a browser via a URI link.
Another example is category_launcher.
Which means that the target activity can
be the initial activity of a task and
is listed in the top level
application launcher.
Intents also have a type feel.
Which specifies the MIME
type of the intents data.
Some examples of MIME types include,
various image formats.
Things like image/png for PNG images,
and image/jpeg or JPG for JPEG images.
There's, there are also various
text formats, such as text/html for
HTML text, or text/plain for
arbitrary text data.
And of course,
if you don't specify a MIME type,
Android will try to infer one for you.
You can set an intents MIME type by
using the setType method passing in
a string that represents
the desired mind type.
You can also set both the data and
the type together by calling
the setDataAndType method.
Intents also have a component field that
identifies the intent's target activity.
And you can set this field if you
know that there is exactly one
activity that should always
receive this intent.
You can set the intent's target component
using one of the intent's constructors,
by passing in a context object,
and a class object
which represents the activity that
should perform the desired operation.
And we'll see a code example
of this in a few minutes.
You can also create an empty intent and
then use one of the setComponent(),
setClass(), or setClassName()
methods to set that target activity.
Intents also have an extras field.
Extras store additional information
associated with the intent.
Now extras are effectively
a map of key-value pairs.
So the target activity has
to know both the name and
the type of any extra data
that it intends to use.
For example, the intent class
defines an extra called EXTRA_EMAIL.
And this extra is used to pass a list
of recipients when sending email.
Now as you can see here,
this code creates an intent,
with the action Intent.ACTION_SEND.
So we want to send some email.
It also adds an extra to that intent.
The extra is named EXTRA_EMAIL.
And in this case it's values include me,
aporter@cs.umd.edu,
ceo@microsoft.com, potus@whitehouse.gov,
and mozart@musician.org.
Now there are several different methods
for setting extras and the specific
form of these methods will depend on
the type of data you want to store.
So, for example, there's one method for
storing a string, one method for
storing an array of floats, and so on.
Another intent field is called flags.
Flags represent information about
how the intent should be handled.
Some built in examples include
flag_activity_no_history.
Which means that when an activity
is started based on this intent,
it shouldn't be put in the history stack.
Another flag is FLAG_DEBUG_LOG_RESOLUTION
which tells Android to print out extra
logging information when this intent is
being processed, and this is a great tool
to use if your intents are not starting
up the activities that you want them to.